Hall Family papers, 1815-1871, 1939.
Congregational Library & Archives
Hall Family papers, 1815-1871, 1939.
1815 1939
MS5425
Congregational Library & Archives
.22 Cubic Feet
(1 legal size document case)
Gordon Hall was a missionary to India who was from Tolland, Massachusetts. While in India he met Margaret Lewis, who had lived there for over 20 years. They would eventually get married and have four kids together, though only one survived into adulthood. That child, first born Nathan and then Gordon, was a minister who served in Wilton, Connecticut and Northampton, Massachusetts. Gordon would marry Emily Baldwin Hall and they would have seven children together. One of those children, Gordon Robert Hall, was a working physician in New York. Samuel and Clarina Bradley Merwin were the parents of Emily Baldwin Hall and lived mainly in New Haven, Connecticut. This collection contains letters to Margaret Lewis Hall as well as letters to and from her son, Gordon Hall, and a letter from Samuel Merwin to Clarina Bradley Merwin. Also included are financial documents related to the Hall Family, including a marriage settlement and a certificate of capital stock.
Hall, Gordon
Hall, Gordon, 1823-1879
Merwin, Samuel, 1781-1856
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library by Gordon Hall in July 2021; 2021-08.
Biographical Information
Gordon Hall was born on April 8, 1784 in Tolland, Massachusetts. His parents were Nathan and Elizabeth Hall. Gordon went to Williams College between 1805 and 1808. After graduation, he worked as a minister in Woodbury, Connecticut from 1809-1810. He also spent some time working in Pittsfield, Massachusetts. Hall would enroll in Andover Theological Seminary in 1810 and eventually be ordained on February 6th, 1812. That same month, the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions sent Hall and four others to India. Upon arrival, Hall went to Bombay with fellow missionary Samuel Nott. He would eventually marry Margaret Lewis in December of 1816. They would have four children together, though only one would survive into adulthood. In 1826, while touring areas of the country with outbreaks of cholera, he contracted the disease and died.
Margaret Lewis Hall was born in Wales on July 20, 1783. She moved to India and while there learned to speak Hindustani. She met Gordon Hall in Bombay and they would marry in 1816. They would have four children together, though only one would survive into adulthood. In 1825, she left with their two sons for Salem, Massachusetts in order to leave them with relatives. One of the sons would die on the journey and when Gordon died the following year, she remained in the United States. She died in Northampton, Massachusetts on January 25, 1868.
Gordon Hall was born Nathan Hall on November 4, 1823 in India. He was the youngest child of Margaret and Gordon and the only one to survive past childhood. At some point he would change his name from Nathan to Gordon. He attended Yale in 1843 and also Yale Theological Seminary in 1847. He served as minister in Wilton, Connecticut from 1848 to 1852 and then at the Edwards Church in Northampton, Massachusetts from 1852 until his death. He received an honorary divinity degree from Amherst College in 1864. Gordon married Emily Baldwin Merwin in 1848 and they had seven children together. Gordon died on November 5, 1879 of typhoid pneumonia.
Gordon Robert Hall was born on September 28, 1849 in Wilton, Connecticut. His mother was Emily Baldwin Hall and father was Gordon Hall. Hall graduated from Amherst College in 1872 and then the College of Physicians and Surgeons in 1880. He was a working physician at Kings County Hospital and a consultant in hospitals in New York. He died on October 23, 1923 in Brooklyn, New York.
Samuel Merwin was the father of Emily Baldwin Hall, who would eventually marry Gordon Hall. He was born on May 21, 1781 and was a minister in New Haven, Connecticut. He died on September 3, 1856 in New Haven.
Clarina Bradley Merwin was the mother of Emily Baldwin Hall, who would eventually marry Gordon hall. She was born in Danbury, Connecticut in 1788 and died in New Haven, Connecticut in 1859.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains letters to Margaret Lewis Hall as well as letters to and from her son, Gordon Hall, and a letter from Samuel Merwin to Clarina Bradley Merwin. Also included are financial documents related to the Hall Family, including a marriage settlement and a certificate of capital stock.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into two series and the records in each series has been arranged chronologically by start date.
Bibliography
Bardwell, Horatio, Memoir of Rev. Gordon Hall, A.M.: one of the first missionaries of the Amer. Board of Comm. for For. Missions, at Bombay. New York: Flagg, Gould, and Newman, 1834. https://archive.org/details/memoirofrevgordofm00bard/page/n7/mode/2up?q=margaret.
Davis, Emerson, Biographical sketches of the Congregational pastors of New England. Boston: Congregational Publishing Society, 1869. https://archive.org/details/biographicalsket04davi/page/n5/mode/2up.
Dr. Gordon Robert Hall. New York Times (New York, NY), Oct. 24, 1923.
Markham, Sandra. Clarina Bradley Taylor Merwin. Findagrave. December 5, 2020. https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/219365173/clarina-bradley-merwin.
The Congregational Yearbook. Boston: Congregational Publishing Society, 1880. https://archive.org/details/congregationalye1880cong/mode/2up.
Letters.; Correspondence.; Hall, Gordon; Hall, Gordon, 1823-1879; Hall, Gordon Robert, 1849-1923; Hall, Gordon, 1784-1826; Hall, Margaret Lewis, 1783-1868; Merwin, Clarina Bradley, 1788-1859
- Letters, 1815 1939; 1815-1871, 1939; 12 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains letters to Margaret Lewis Hall, wife of missionary Gordon Hall, as well as letters to and from their son, also named Gordon Hall. Also included is a letter from Samuel Merwin to Clarina Bradley Merwin.
  - Letter from Samuel Merwin to Clarina Bradley Merwin, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Biographical Information
    Samuel and Clarina Merwin were married and had several children, including Emily Baldwin Merwin. Emily would eventually marry Gordon Hall.
  - Letters to Margaret Lewis Hall, 1824 1826; 1824-1826 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellany Letters, 1826 1939; 1826, 1864, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Margaret Lewis Hall, 1827 1828; 1827-1828 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Margaret Lewis Hall, 1829 1830; 1829-1830 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Margaret Lewis Hall, 1831 1834; 1831-1834 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Margaret Lewis Hall, 1835 1842; 1835-1842 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to and from Gordon Hall, 1842 1845; 1842-1845 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to and from Gordon Hall, 1848 1850; 1848-1850 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to and from Gordon Hall, 1851 1853; 1851-1853 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to and from Gordon Hall, 1864, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter from Gordon Hall to his son, September 26, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Finance, 1834 1865; 1834, 1865; 2 Folders
  This series contains financial documents related to the Hall Family, including a marriage settlement and a certificate of capital stock.
  - Marriage Settlement of Gordon Hall and Margaret Lewis, November 1, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Capital Stock, August 31, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 12)